<DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920324-0019
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920324-0019.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   No Expectations:
   Working Class Culture
   Erodes Britain's Rank
   In a Unified Europe
   ---
   Ancient Cycle of Manual Toil,
   Hopelessness and the Dole
   Still Holds In Hartlepool
   ---
   At Home With Andy Capp
   ----
   By Tony Horwitz
   Staff Reporter of The Wall Street Journal
</HL>
<DATE>
02/11/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<CO>
   LABOR
</CO>
<IN>
INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC NEWS AND STATISTICS (IEN)
</IN>
<NS>
EDUCATION ISSUES (EDU)
INTERNATIONAL ECONOMIC NEWS AND ANALYSIS (IEN)
LABOR, PERSONNEL ISSUES (LAB)
</NS>
<RE>
EUROPEAN COMMUNITY (EC)
EUROPE (EU)
FRANCE (FR)
GERMANY (GE)
PORTUGAL (PO)
GREAT BRITAIN (UK)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   HARTLEPOOL, England -- In a black slush of seaweed and
coal slag, the shovel is passing from father to son.
   "Use your whole body when you lift," Thomas Dawes says.
His 15-year-old son, Paul, heaves soggy coal onto a truck. It
is low tide on a winter night, when the slag dumped in the
water by nearby mines coats the beach of this North Sea port.
Scraping madly in the frigid surf, the Dawes can skim three
tons of cheap fuel -- worth about $40 -- before the tide
rolls in.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Paul, a slight youth with blistered hands and chapped
lips, has been "humping sea coal" for only two weeks. "School
was a bore," he says, stooping in the dark for another load
of coal. "Least now, I'm doing what suits me. Like Dad."
   For generations in England's industrial cities, it went
something like this: Son left school at 14 or 15 and followed
his father into the steelworks, shipyard or coal pit. Today,
after decades of decline, those traditional jobs are almost
gone. Yet the old pattern persists. Working-class children
leave school at the earliest chance: to join the dole queue,
to train in dwindling trades or to do Dickensian jobs such as
sea coaling.
   "We're drifting into the backwaters of Europe," says John
Saville, an economic historian at Hull University. "If things
don't change, we'll become an ill-educated outpost with
nothing to sell but our heritage."
   The roots of this malaise go much deeper than the current
recession (by some measures, the country's worst downturn
since the 1930s). England's rigid class structure, its
exclusive education system and its welfare state all
reinforce a stagnant status quo. This may bode further
decline as Europe's economy integrates and jobs become more
complex. About 70% of French youths, and 81% of Western
Germans, remain in full-time education at the age of 18. In
Britain the figure is 36%. The proportion of British workers
with skills is below even traditional laggards such as
Portugal.
   Hartlepool, in England's northern rust belt, is a window
into this country's resilient working-class culture. A
century ago, this was England's third busiest port, thriving
on the export of coal, iron and other products. But the
decline of Britain's empire and trade gutted the industrial
north. This city of 94,000 now is dotted with derelict docks,
boarded-up shops and grim housing projects with unemployment
at 17.3%.
   "It's a pit," says 15-year-old Paul Weldon, echoing the
view of many of his peers. A want ad in the local paper, for
a gravedigger, attracts 120 applicants. Entertainment also is
scarce. The last movie theater closed in 1983.
   Yet the population here is relatively stable, and
neighborhoods are almost village-like in their provincialism.
With the cheapest compact cars in England costing almost
$10,000, and gasoline $4 a gallon, few low-income families in
Hartlepool own cars. London, 250 miles away, is for most a
distant place seen only on TV serials. Even the coal-mining
towns just five miles up the coast are viewed as alien turf,
inhabited by "pit yackers," so-called because their accent
and slang are hard for Hartlepudlians to understand.
   "People here don't move from one street to the next,
unless the bank takes their house," says Wayne Smith, sipping
a pint of beer at the Red Admiral pub, as fellow drinkers
indulge in renditions of "Que Sera" and "Make the World Go
Away."
   Mr. Smith, who is 19 and unemployed, spent the day typing
his resume. But since he doesn't drive -- no family car to
practice with, no money for lessons -- he's disqualified for
many jobs, and also can't easily reach other towns. Yet he
hasn't considered relocating. "I'm not a traveling man," he
says. Apart from a soccer match in Newcastle, 25 miles north,
he's barely left the county.
   Such immobility is social as well as geographic. The
"accursed itch of class difference" decried by George Orwell
in 1937 still infects almost every aspect of life and
language. In a recent survey, two-thirds of Britons
identified themselves as working class. Decades of Labor
government haven't changed this, nor have Tory declarations
that their goal is the creation of a classless society.
   If anything, inequality is widening. The top 20% in
Britain now command 42% of the nation's total income, the
bottom fifth just 8%. This isn't as stark as in America,
where the top fifth possess 47%, the poorest just 3.9%, but
it's the biggest gap in Britain since 1949. "There has been a
reversal in one decade of the changes in the previous three,"
says Anthony Atkinson, an expert on income distribution at
the London School of Economics.
   Social standing, though, is as much self-image as economic
status. In Hartlepool, people are proud to be working class.
Or upper working class. Or lower working class. Or "scruffs"
or "scroungers." The divisions within the working class
number at least five.
   "I'm basically middle working class but my attitudes are
more upper working class," says William Adamson, a miner's
son who has been in and out of factory jobs. "I mean, I make
the same money as me dad, but I wouldn't talk to him about
the latest news from Yugoslavia."
   Reg Smythe, who grew up in Hartlepool's slums and went on
to create the cartoon "Andy Capp," widely syndicated in the
U.S., says the working class used to differentiate itself by
its shoes. The upper tier had "proper shoes," the next rank
had boots, the next "plimps" (sneakers), and so on, to bare
feet -- Mr. Smythe's group. "We were the only ones who didn't
have anyone to look down on," he says.
   Mr. Smythe left school at 14 and later moved to London,
where he drew Andy Capp, which he regards as a documentary
portrait of working-class life. Now 74, Mr. Smythe has moved
back to Hartlepool and finds little changed. The wealthy
drink at the town's "top end" and poorer ones at the "bottom
end," even though there's no hill in Hartlepool. And while
industrial jobs are mostly gone, the culture survives.
   "I can still go down to the Boilermakers' Club and get two
or three ideas just listening to the conversation," says Mr.
Smythe, who still draws Andy Capp daily. "The mindset's
exactly the same."
   In a way, so is Mr. Smythe's. When regional boosters asked
his permission to dress Andy Capp in coat and tie for
promotional cartoons, Mr. Smythe refused. And though now a
wealthy man, living in Hartlepool's nicest district, he
abjures "the wine-and-cheese crowd" and still regards himself
as working class.
   "It's like going to another country and thinking you can
escape," Mr. Smythe says. "You can't. You take yourself with
you."
   If there is one institution that most clearly reflects and
sustains class, it is English education. Though schools have
become more democratic in recent decades, this is still a
system that winnows a chosen few, relegating the rest to
inferior status. Students begin specializing at 14 and must
clear steep, exam-oriented barriers at 16 and 18. Only one in
five students makes it to a university. Working-class kids,
at often overcrowded and underfunded schools, can't easily
compete with students in better districts, or at schools such
as Eton.
   "Because we remain a class society, we make this
tremendous distinction between the sheep and the goats,
between the academic and the vocational," says Sir Claus
Moser, warden of Wadham College at Oxford University. "We set
hurdles in front of children that most know they can't jump."
   At the Manor School in Hartlepool, 80% end their academic
studies at 16. Out of a class of 150, only four, on average,
make it to a university.
   Teachers blame the system, but also a home environment
that puts little emphasis on learning. In a school of 750
students, only 10 parents attend monthly PTA meetings.
Traditionally, with apprenticeships and jobs almost assured
at 16, there was little advantage to staying in school, and
this ethos persists. "The attitude is still, `God made them
high and low, and everyone knows his place,' " says Pat Bell,
a Manor School teacher. "When I push clever students, their
parents complain that I'm only making them big-headed."
   In her morning "assertiveness" class, 15- and 16-year-olds
discuss their plans for next year. Out of 25, all but two
hope to work or train at low-skilled jobs. Asked if any have
considered business or professional careers, Julie Kidson
guffaws.
   "We're looking at the real world, aren't we?" says the
15-year-old, who wants to be a nanny. "We know we aren't
going to make the grade. So why not get out of school and get
on with it?"
   As she and her classmates see it, university is reserved
for "posh kids" who go to the right schools, "get pushed by
their parents," and inherit "the creamy part" of the job
pool. "They can always go work for the family firm, can't
they?" one boy says. Another, whose father is unemployed,
says he'd feel guilty staying in school "instead of bringing
home money."
   Yet asked to fantasize that they have the grades and funds
to do anything, the students don't change the jobs they'd
seek: roofer, cleaner, clerk, pipe fitter.
   Jackie Middleton, a teacher at the Brierton School, says
that at age 11 or 12, some students still dream of becoming
pop or sports stars. But by 16, fantasies don't cross their
radar screen. Even so, after hearing the list of
working-class jobs her students say they're headed for, Ms.
Middleton says they're shooting too high.
   "For a lot of them, when they finish their training, there
won't be jobs," she says. "But why pour water on their
parade?"
   For young Hartlepudlians who can't find work, Britain's
welfare state buffers the unemployed from the bleak poverty
of American inner-cities -- and of north England just a
generation ago. The region's dark, Satanic mills are mostly
gone, as are its slums, cleared for suburban-style housing
projects. All Britons have access to free medical care. An
unemployed couple with two children receives about $160 a
week, plus free rent, free school meals, free medicine, even
"cold weather" payments if the temperature falls below 32
degrees for seven days in a row. While crime rates in the
north are Britain's highest, the streets still are crowded at
night. There were no murders in Hartlepool last year. (In
Youngstown, Ohio, a U.S. industrial city of identical size,
there were 59.)
   "There's a real sense of belonging here," says Margaret
Rae, a benefits counselor in Hartlepool. "People have a very
tight network to fall back on."
   Britain's safety net, though, has a sticky underside:
long-term dependency. Because of the benefits structure, an
unemployed parent of two in Hartlepool must find a job paying
almost $300 a week to improve on the dole. The few jobs
available here typically pay $150 to $250 (there is no
minimum wage in Britain). The result, says Ms. Rae, "is that
there isn't much incentive to find work. When people here get
offers, we often have to show them that they're better off
saying no." In the area she covers, 50% of residents are
jobless, and most have been for 15 years or more.
   Other social workers say that many men trained in trades
are reluctant to take service jobs, a disdain they often
communicate to their sons. The Rev. William Hall, who runs a
community center near Hartlepool, takes this gloom one step
further. He believes Britain must accept that many citizens
will never find employment. Instead of job counseling, his
center offers ways for "people to fulfill their potential
outside of paid work," such as a "tool library" that lends
saws and hammers for home carpentry.
   Margaret Thatcher's calls in the 1980s for an "enterprise
culture" have had scant impact. Laborers sought opportunities
elsewhere, only to end up where they started. Danny Graham,
an unemployed steelworker, was one of many northerners who
decided to "go down London." He and three friends found work
pulling asbestos out of hospital walls. But they couldn't
find affordable housing. "So we parked me car behind the
animal lab at the hospital and slept in it. Two in front, two
in back." They lasted three weeks.
   Entrepreneurship also hasn't taken root. Only 9% of
northern workers are self-employed. "Enterprise culture?
You're looking at it," chuckles Fred Medland, gesturing at a
wooden cart piled with bent baby carriages, an old sink and
other junk. Mr. Medland is one of Hartlepool's "rag and
bones" men, clomping down residential streets on horse-drawn
carts, yelling for people to bring out old clothes or "any
scrap iron]" Collecting everything from rusted tricycles to
discarded artificial legs, the rag and bones men sell their
loads at local scrap yards, which crush or bundle the goods
for reprocessing.
   Mr. Medland, whose partner wears a frayed tweed suit he
salvaged from the refuse, typically earns $5 for a morning's
work. "It's enough to keep me going until tomorrow," says the
64-year-old former steelworker. He sleeps near his horse, in
a stable perched on a plot known as the "slag banks," where
the now-closed steelworks used to dump waste metal.
   For most rag and bones men, collecting scrap is a "fiddle
job" -- slang for unreported work that illegally supplements
the dole. Such jobs, which include windowwashing or painting
and decorating, are an English mainstay, just one of the many
ways that low-income people have always scraped by.
   In a country where wages are similar to the U.S., but
prices much higher, even those "in work" make do with less.
Most smokers in Hartlepool roll their own cigarettes, much
cheaper than paying $3.80 for a regular pack. Nationwide,
barely half of those polled in a recent survey listed
telephones and TV sets as items "which all adults should be
able to afford." Two pairs of all-weather shoes were deemed
an unnecessary luxury by 26%. One-fifth said they didn't eat
in a restaurant as much as once a month.
   "Struggling is a way of life," says Jean Clayton, a
secretary earning $167 a week at Hartlepool's nuclear plant,
as she and her daughter shop at the "Queen's Nearly New Dress
Agency." Ms. Clayton went to work when her husband lost his
job five years ago. The family hasn't purchased furniture or
new clothes since then.
   Others save by growing food. At Easington, a mining
village of back-to-back cottages near Hartlepool, residents
rent small gardens wedged between the main shaft and the
railroad. "For most of us, it used to be a hobby -- you know,
growing the biggest cabbage for a show prize," says Doug
Gray, a factory worker, tilling the sooty soil. "Now, it's a
little extra at dinnertime."
   The Easington mine dumps a mix of stone and slag straight
into the North Sea, adding to the deposits of "sea coal" that
the Dawes family and others in Hartlepool collect for a
living. The land between the low and high tide mark, and
anything on it, technically belongs to the Crown.
   "If the queen wants it, she can come and get it," says the
elder Dawes, Thomas, sloshing through the sulfur-smelling
surf, amidst the refuse of the Industrial Age: rubber belts,
bolts, rivets, bits of wire. Other men scurry through the
dark, staking claims by standing their shovels in the densest
rivulets of coal.
   Working both tides each day, Mr. Dawes can make about
$5,000 a year. He pays "pocket money" to Paul, who is the
fourth of his sons to work there. "They all come back to the
beach in the end," Mr. Dawes says. "It's what they know."
   The Dawes family lives almost rent-free in a subsidized
brick house, in a project known as Rogues' End because of its
rampant crime. "You have to keep an eye on your laundry line,
so someone doesn't pinch your clothes," says Thomas's wife,
Christine, who cleans part-time at a chemical factory.
   In the evening, the family gathers around the TV with
their four children still living at home; the other three
live less than a mile away. Mark, 25, has been seacoaling on
his own, and his face and clothes are streaked with grime.
   After a dinner of egg and butter sandwiches, Thomas plucks
the tide chart from the top of the TV. "High water's at 10
past midnight," he says. Mark nods. Paul picks at the blister
on his middle finger. At 4 a.m., after a video and a short
snooze, they'll gather their shovels for another shift of
sea-coaling. The Dawes's youngest child, 10-year-old Andrew,
asks if he can come, too.
   Christine goes to clear dishes. "I'd always dreamed that
one of the boys would get off the beach and make something of
himself," she says. "But if you're working class, you just
can't move up, can you?"
   (See related letters: "Letters to the Editor: We're All
Right, Jack" -- WSJ March 24, 1992)
   920211-0122
</TEXT>
</DOC>

